Benjamin Kopman Papers / Collection
Benjamin Kopman Papers / Collection
1911-1962
Kopman, Benjamin, b. 1887
2.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American Jewish painter, lithographer, etcher, illustrator, sculptor.Born in Russia. Correspondence (1911-1962), including a series of letters (1936-1958), some in scrapbook form, by Kopman to his art dealer, G.D. Thompson; manuscript poems, and prose, some in Yiddish; legal and financial papers; sketches; and photographs of Kopman's work and his family. Incoming letters, arranged alphabetically, include those from the Art Institute of Chicago, David Burliuk, the Federal Art Project, Rockwell Kent, Katharine Kuh, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art, Clifford Odets, the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, the Phillips Memorial Gallery, Hugo Robus, Frederic F. Sherman, Raphael Soyer, the Whitney Museum of American Art, and Carl Zigrosser.
149110
Biographical History
Benjamin Kopman (1887-1965) was a Russian-American painter, graphic artist, and illustrator. Born in Russia, he emigrated with his parents to the United States in 1903. As a youngster, he was tutored by the artist Abel Pen, but he had no formal education. In 1905, he studied for six semesters at the National Academy of Art in New York. He became a citizen of the United States in 1913.
Kopman's work is represented in the collections of the great museums of the United States and Israel. He illustrated the Book of the Month Club edition of Crime and Punishment and Frankenstein. In 1945, he was awarded the Gold Medal of the Philadelphia Academy. Although unpublished, Mr. Kopman was also a writer and poet.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
This collection consists of two related sets of material: the papers of Mr. Kopman, and some additions to the collection made by Mrs. G.D. Thompson, wife of Mr. Kopman's art dealer. The former are referred to as the Benjamin Kopman Papers; the latter are known as the Benjamin Kopman Collection.
The Benjamin Kopman Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material.
Correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing. Subject files consists of documents, accounts, passports and photographs. Manuscripts contains drawings, essays, journals, artwork, prose, and some few items in Yiddish. Published material consists of articles, a book, clippings, exhibit cataloges, and photographs.
The Benjamin Kopman Collection contains correspondence, one subject file, and a few manuscripts and published material.
Correspondence consists of outgoing only -- Kopman's letters to G.D. Thompson. The one Subject file contains negatives of photographs of Kopman's work. Manuscripts contains drawings, poems and prose. Published material contains clippings and exhibit material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Benjamin Kopman Papers: Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author; outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically; correspondence of others is arranged alphabetically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by type, and within each type, alphabetically by title. Manuscripts of others are placed at the end of the series. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type.
Benjamin Kopman Collection: Correspondence is arranged chronologically; scrapbooks have some overlapping of dates. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by type and alphabetically by title within type. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Burliuk, David, 1882-1967.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Kopman, Benjamin, b. 1887 -- Archives.; Kuh, Katharine.; Odets, Clifford, 1906-1963.; Robus, Hugo, 1885-1964.; Sherman, Frederic Fairchild, 1874-1940.; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987.; Thompson, G. David.; Zigrosser, Carl, 1891-; Art Institute of Chicago.; Federal Art Project.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts.; Phillips Memorial Gallery.; Whitney Museum of American Art.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Jewish artists -- United States.; Illustrators -- United States.; Jews, American.; Lithographers, United States.; Lithography, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Russian Americans.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Essays.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photonegatives.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Artists.; Illustrators.; Lithographers.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, in part, of Mrs. G.D. Thompson. Additions to the Benjamin Kopman Papers given by Mrs. G.D. Thompson
Inventory
- Benjamin Kopman Papers
  - Biographical material
    - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - A-B (Box 1)
      - Art Institute of Chicago, 1914; 1920-21,; 1939,; 1950 (Box 1)
      - Baldinger, Wallace S., 1937; 1939 (Box 1)
      - Book of the Month Club, 1942; 1945,; 1946,; 1956 (Box 1)
      - Brooklyn Museum, 1917; 1939,; 1949,; 1962 (Box 1)
      - Burluik, David, 1952 (Box 1)
      - C-F (Box 1)
      - Carnegie Institute, 1938; 1940,; 1944,; 1947-49,; undated (Box 1)
      - Cheney, Martha, 1938 (Box 1)
      - Fisher, William F., 1913; undated (Box 1)
      - Fulton, James G., 1946; Congressman (Box 1)
      - G-L (Box 1)
      - Kent, Rockwell, 1939 (Box 1)
      - Knvedler, Leinie, 1917-22; undated (Box 1)
      - Kopman, Benjamin, 1948 (Box 1)
      - Kopman, Diana, 1946; undated; daughter (Box 1)
      - Kuh, Katharine, 1936-37; 1939,; undated (Box 1)
      - Landau, R., 1930 (Box 1)
      - Lewisohn, Dana A., 1939; 1947 (Box 1)
      - M-O (Box 1)
      - Macbeth, William, 1914-17; 1922 (Box 1)
      - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1939; 1945,; 1949,; 1950 (Box 1)
      - Museum of Modern Art, 1932; 1949,; 1950,; 1951 (Box 1)
      - New Art Circle, 1930; 1937,; 1945-46,; 1949,; undated (Box 1)
      - Odets, Clifford, 1946-47; 1950,; undated (Box 1)
      - P-Y (Box 1)
      - Parker, Woodruff J., 1919-21 (Box 2)
      - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1913; 1917,; 1935,; 1939,; 1946,; 1961 (Box 2)
      - Porter, James W. (Box 2)
      - Phillips Memorial Gallery, 1939 (Box 2)
      - Reis, Bernard, 1931 (Box 2)
      - Robus, Hugo, 1911; 1915 (Box 2)
      - Rockefeller, Abby, 1932 (Box 2)
      - Sherman, Frederick F., 1915; 1916,; 1917 (Box 2)
      - Soyer, Raphael, undated (Box 2)
      - Thompson, G.D., 1936 (Box 2)
      - Thompson, G.D., 1937 (Box 2)
      - Thompson, G.D., 1938 (Box 2)
      - Thompson, G.D., 1939 (Box 2)
      - Thompson, G.D., 1945-48; 1954,; undated (Box 2)
      - Warbury, Edward M., 1939; sec'y F.Levine (Box 2)
      - Whitney Museum, 1932; 1935-38,; 1954 (Box 2)
      - Wyatt, Beverly, 1945-47; undated (Box 2)
      - Zigrosser, Carl, 1923; 1951,; undated (Box 2)
      - Works Progress Administration, 1935; 1938-39, (Box 2)
      - Young, J.W., 1918; 1920 (Box 2)
      - Unidentifiable, 1916; undated (Box 2)
    - Outgoing
      - 1938 (Box 2)
      - Not sent, 1911; 1920,; 1922,; 1924,; 1934,; 1935,; 1937,; 1938,; 1941,; 1956-58,; 1961,; 1962,; undated (Box 2)
    - Of others
      - 1918, 1947-49 (Box 2)
  - Subject file
    - Accounts, documents, passports (Box 3)
    - Photographs
      - Kopman's work (Box 3)
      - Kopman and family (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts
    - Drawings (Box 3)
    - Essays
      - Art (Box 3)
      - Autobiographical (Box 3)
      - General (Box 3)
    - Journals (Box 3)
    - Poems (Box 3)
    - Prose
      - "Ben Venoo" (Box 3)
      - "Days in the Life of the Unholy Glatius" (Box 3)
      - "The Posthumous Diary of Glatius, A Pound of Body For a Pound of Emotion" (Box 3)
      - "Glatius, the Casual Journal of a Painter Poet" (Box 4)
      - "The Murderer" (Box 4)
    - Yiddish (Box 4)
    - Of others, poems by W.M. Fisher (Box 4)
  - Published material
    - Articles about Kopman (Box 4)
    - Articles by Kopman (Box 4)
    - Book, about Kopman (Box 4)
    - Exhibition catalogues (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings about Kopman (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings by Kopman (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, Yiddish (Box 4)
    - Pictures (Box 4)
- Benjamin Kopman Collection
  - Correspondence, Kopman letters to G.D. Thompson
    - 1937, 1939-41, 1946, 1933, 1956, 1958, undated (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1936-39 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1938; 1940-48, (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Subject file
    - Negatives, Kopman's work (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts
    - Drawings by Kopman (Box 5)
    - Poems by Kopman (Box 5)
    - Prose by Kopman
      - "A Few Highlights in My Life" (Box 5)
      - "Days in the Life of the Unholy Glatius" (Box 5)
  - Published material
    - Exhibits, Kopman and others (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings about Kopman (Box 5)